[MUSIC]
斯坦福大学. >> 好的,
欢迎来到 CS193P 的第五课，
现在是 2016 年春。
今天我们首先要做的是在之前的工程中增加一点功能，然后
看看效果。 我将会为你展示一些 Xcode 可视化界面中
很酷的特性，
这部分内容我们会在 Storyboard 上完成。
然后我们将开始讨论如何正确实现 FACEIT 中的
视图、控制器和模型。
好的, 现在如果你看了 FACEIT 中
控制器的代码。 你会发现它是空白的，
什么都没有。我们需要在上面完成一些工作。
现在先回到幻灯片上来
我要讲解手势的相关知识点, 它是 UIView 的输入端。
我会演示一个在 FACEIT 上添加手势的 Demo。
然后如果时间允许的话，
我会在幻灯片上讲解多重 MVC
它是构建更大型的应用的入口。 好吧
以上就是今天的主要内容。 让我们直接进入 demo 环节
我要开始做我刚刚谈到的那两件事,
一个是界面生成器。 另一个是
我们的 FaceViewController 的模型，
正常来说这个模型要描述一个面部表情。
好的，现在我们来到 FaceView，
这是我们上节课最后停留的部分。
我会快速地强化 FaceView 的功能，让它变得更酷。
如果你还记得上一次我们对 FaceView 上的嘴巴
进行了一些配置。 我们可以让它微笑、
皱眉并且拥有两只眼睛，很不错。我现在要增加两样东西，
首先我可以让它闭上眼睛。
我要做的另外一件事是:给它加上眉毛。
我完成起来非常地快，
因为我所需要的代码不需要对现有的的代码做较大改动，
只需要新增一些代码，
跟女人画眉毛相比要省事得多。
因此我需要定义一组新的公有变量，
因为有一些东西需要可配置。
一个属性表示眼睛是否是睁开的, 这是一个布尔变量。
我将把眼睛的初始状态设置为睁开，怎么样？
true 是它的默认值。 然后我定义另一个新属性
取名为 eyebrowTilt, 怎么样?
这是一个 double 类型的变量. 初始值设置为 0.0。
它的定义类比于嘴巴弯曲的弧度。
我们让默认曲率为 0。
-1代表很郁闷，1代表完全放松的眉毛, 怎么样?
非常像我们对嘴巴的曲率做的设置。
先来让眼睛睁开。很简单。
在之前画眼睛的路径中， 你可以看到我们用一个圆的路径代表眼睛。
这解释了为什么眼睛是圆的。
所以如果眼睛睁开的话， 我打算还这么做，
如何? 我们继续用圆来表示。
但是如果眼睛是闭上的, 我会用另一个图形来表示
只使用一条线。
如果眼睛是闭合的话我会画一条水平的线。
非常简单。看这里， BezierPath，
移动到一个点上,画一条线。然后画眉毛，
如你所见，我们有眼睛的路径，
有嘴巴的路径，所以我仅仅需要为眉毛画一个路径
我想我可以用这里的代码！现在这就是我们的眉毛的路径
它很简单. 画了一条直线
这条线是倾斜的。 倾斜程度取决于我们设置的斜率
当然了我们还需要向比例中增加一些静态变量
代表眉毛相对于旋转中心点的偏移距离
就像我们设置的
其他与半径相关的信息。
现在我们有了方法 pathForBrow, 就像定义
pathForEye 和 pathForMouth 那样， 让我们继续
绘制它们。 我要绘制的路径是, 眉毛, 左边那条,
绘制, 然后绘制右边的眉毛。
大功告成。
让我们继续并且运行程序, 看看我们能看到什么,
现在我们应该有眉毛了。 好的,
耶, 看我们有眉毛了, 它们有一点可爱。
我们应该也可以让眼睛闭上了。
所以我要把 eyesOpen 设为 false。
看下有没有起作用,起作用了, 眼睛闭上了。
我们可以把 eyebrowTilt 设置成..嗯..就-0.5吧。
看下效果。好的,
增加了倾斜的效果. 所以你看到了眉毛的效果,
我们可以做出更多的面部表情。
这就是我把他放在这的原因。
当涉及到面部表情时
我们有更多可操作的选项。
我要在这设置更多的选项。 其中一个可以是
我在这里定义的一些常量，比如颜色总是蓝色的。
我不希望这样。 所以我把它改成一个变量,
我准备给变量取名为 color。 我在这里定义一个变量 Color
它的类型是 UIColor。
并且我设置它的默认值是蓝色。 唔 UIColor,
默认是 blueColor。然后我也会把线的宽度定义为一个变量
怎么样? 现在, 我们的线宽一直是 0.5
所以我把默认值设成 5.0.
但是我会把所有用到 5.0 这个常量的地方替换成这个变量,
让我们完成这个工作。 一共有 1, 2, 3, 4. 好的, 我们替换了四处.
眉毛, 眼睛, 我们的嘴, 和骨头. okay?
我们增强了 faceView 的外部调用性, 好的。
所有这些公开的方法都是一个控制器
可能用到的。 因为我们都是视图的一部分, okay.
我们是一个通用的脸部绘制视图, 所以我们可以被
任何想要绘制面部的控制器所使用。 Okay?
哪一个是我们已经拥有了的控制器呢？
这里绘制了一张脸。 不过
如果我们查看这里我们自己的控制器的话,
控制器绘制一张脸但是对这张脸做任何配置, okay?
它拥有了 storyboard 提供的视图,
我们要把脸绘制在上面, 但是没有做其他的工作。
我们一分钟就能完成。 现在， 有一件令人苦恼的事情，
当我们查看我们的 storyboard。
Okay, 这里是我们的 storyboard。
我们看不到我们绘制的脸，并且我们只有一个 MVC
我们知道它是一个脸，可是
我们看不到。但是
如果我们有 20 个控制器,
这里会有一张脸，那里又会有一整套别的东西。
如果脸能在这里展示出来，岂不是很酷？ Okay。
等下我们会在可视化构造器上看到它。 实际上，
很容易办到。你需要做的就是到你的视图上,
okay? 你自定一个 UIView, 取名 faceView.并且它的定义上面加上
@IBdesignable 关键字。 如果你声明了 @IBdesignable,
可视化构造器会认为你想要
绘制这个东西。
所以你可以看到, 代码会被编译并且绘制。
在我的 storyboard 上，脸出现了。 okay。
这真的很酷。但是还有一件不太酷的事情，
如果我点击我的 faceView 并且打开检查器。
我只能检查 faceView 从 View 继承来的属性
比如像它的背景色这样的属性, 没错吧?
如果我能检查像眉毛、最的曲率
以及颜色和比例的话那就很酷了。
这里是不是该倾斜
如果我能在可视化构造器中完成所有这些属性的设置那就太酷了。
也许我可以按照我的想法来初始化一张脸，
可视化构造器可以实现。
如果你回顾 faceView.
所有的这一切都在这里, 它们是可设置的,
你只需在它们前面加上 @IBInspectable。
Okay, 这代表该属性会被显示在观察器中。
因此我把所有的这些属性都设置为可观察的，
给这些家伙们都加上 inspectable。 Okay. 现在可以回到
可视化构造器中了。 你打开这里
你依旧能看到所有 View 相关的属性。
但是现在我们拥有 faceView 中的东西了， 所以
我可以把比例设置为 0.5. Okay, 这使得人脸变小了。
或者我可以把颜色设置成橘黄色。 Okay,
洛杉矶巨人队的颜色。好吧! 我可以把线宽从5改为2
线就变细了， okay?
在这里我可以设置嘴巴的曲率, 设置为 -0.5。
对把, 眼睛是否睁开? 睁开状态?
让我们继续, okay,看到了吗? 比例变回0.9。
好的, 我们做到了，这很酷。
实际上， 当我们第一次运行程序,
它就会应用这些值。 让我们继续并且运行程序
你会看到屏幕上会显示相同的脸。
线条、颜色、线宽以及所有的这些属性。
就像我们在检查器上设置的任何其他属性一样。
比如背景颜色或者其他诸如此类的属性。 当然，当我们运行时
这些属性都会被初始化,
okay? 现在， 有个小细节要注意
当你要设置可变属性为 IBInspectable 时
你必须显式地声明它们的类型。 你看，像这里，
大部分我原本都不需要声明类型的, 对吧?
Swift 可以通过赋值推断出 Double 类型。 但是
如果你正在使用 IBInspectable,
你必须显式地写出类型， 因为可视化构造器不能推断它们的类型。
Swift 可以，但是可视化构造器不能。
所以你需要明确类型， okay。
这只是一个小的需要注意的点。 Okay, 现在，另外一件我要说到的事情是
这里的视图，如果某个人设置了它的比例，
okay, 在代码里面设置的。
控制器在这里, 我们在视图的代码中设置比例。
实际上没有起到任何效果。
Okay,屏幕上不会有变化， 这是为什么呢?
因为当我们把比例设置为 0.5 时,
你所做的只是修改了这个变量, 你没有做其他的事情,
okay? 因此当变量变为 0.5
人脸的视图进行重绘, 它会被绘制的更小
但是重绘的事件没有被触发。 所以任何时候
你允许这些公共的变量可以被修改的时候,
你需要在属性改变时重绘视图。
Okay, 现在我们该怎么做? 我们用之前讲到的属性观察器
来实现这个功能。
还记得 didSet 和 willSet 吗? 它们都是一小段代码
这种情况下每当变量被赋值或者访问的时候就会触发,
okay? 因此如果该变量被赋值
然后会进入 didSet 代码段, 我想要重绘, 那么我该如何重绘?
也许我需要调用 self.drawRect 我要这么做吗? 不,
在类中这样做会失败， 因为我们永远都不能调用
drawRect。 我们说过使用 setNeedsDisplay 替代， okay，
setNeedsDisplay 的作用是我们告诉系统， 我需要被重绘，谢谢。
okay。 重绘会在未来的某个时刻执行,
非常接近的时刻，但是是在未来.
现在, 这种做法非常普遍。 通常我们会清除掉一些换行，
然后把代码摆放到同一行。
Okay, 就像这样。
我们要在所有的变量后面增加观察器。
它要占用注释的位置了。
在这里摆放一个。 这里也是相同的操作，你很容易发现
它会造成屏幕的空间有些挤。
好的, 所有的这些变量,
如果有人设置了它们, 就会引起重绘。
如果变量中的三个或四个可以一次性地进行重绘那该多酷
而不会引起三四次的重复绘制。
它会不断地说,
我需要被显示，我需要被显示，
我需要被显示。
但它不会真正地被显示，直到一段时间后
它们才会被一次性地重绘。
所以延迟可以提升性能，
对这种问题不要太过于重视，这不是主要原因。
实际上 setNeedsDisplay 方法本来就是这样设计的, 不过
这只是其中的一个原因, okay? 每个人都理解了吗?
Okay, 我们几乎经常会用到 didSet。
现在你会看到我们在控制器中
因为一些其他的原因使用 didSet
okay? 不过 didSet 真的是超级方便！
好吧, okay 让我们来聊聊控制器，
它需要一个模型， okay。 我已经创建好了一个简单的类
叫做 FacialExpression， 现在我把它拖进工程。
我把它复制进来, okay? 当你向工程总拖拽东西的时候,
你几乎总是会把这一项选中。
所以注意一下, 你希望它拷贝进来,
你不希望它链接到别的东西上面
大部分情况下都是这样。
所以我要把这个小小的 FacialExpression 拷贝进来.
让我们来看看 FacialExpression。
你会在这里看到 FacialExpression，它是我们的模型。
看到了吗，它不是 UI 方面的东西，它仅仅引入了 foundation。
它完全地与 UI 分离。 它对一张脸的描述
和 face view 不同。 Okay,
face view 考虑的是嘴巴的曲率、眼睛的弧度以及
这方面的东西。完全不包含这个模型里的东西。
它包含了眉毛的信息，但是只有 Relaxed, Normal, Furrowed这样的描述。
这三个状态是它唯一知道的。
嘴巴也是一样。 它的状态是 Frown, Smirk, Neutral, Grin 以及 Smile。
它就是这样，不包含嘴的曲率。
它甚至不知道曲率什么，
okay? 有一件很有趣的事情，你看到了吗这些都是枚举?
请注意我在枚举中定义了方法， okay?
我不打算讨论这些方法的实现.
如果你读了作业题目,
你应该可以计算出这些。
我在枚举中定义了方法。 但是
面部表情依然只有眼睛、眉毛和嘴巴。
okay,使用了这些枚举来表达。
枚举中的一部分，比如眼睛，包含了 FaceView 中没有出现的状态。
FaceView并没有包含一个眯着的眼睛。
它只知道如何控制眼睛的睁开与闭合。
这里的要点是模型需要被控制器解释给视图
okay?
此外，控制器必须弄清楚， okay,
一个 relaxed 的眉毛是什么意思? 好的，
对脸的视图来说，它意味着眉毛的某种倾斜程度,
所以控制器需要把 relaxed 解释给视图，
看到了吗? 所以这里就解释了控制器在 MVC 中的原始角色
就是把模型
解释给视图。
它也会把视图中的输入值解释给模型
我们会在讲到手势的时候见到， okay.
这就是控制器的原始目的。
所以让我们的控制器来做这件事吧。
我们把 facial expression 转换成
视图中的信息， okay。 所以在控制器中，我们要做的第一件事
就是在这里创建一个变量，
它是一个指向模型的指针, 它是 FacialExpression 类型的
okay。 我们甚至
会把它初始化为某种面部表情。
记住，我们使用的 FacialExpression，
是一个结构体,我们可以使用免费得到的构造器。 我,
顺便提一句，我可以推断它的类型。 我不需要写出来，
对吗? 我得到的这个免费的构造器中,
我们让眼睛睁开, 然后是眉毛。
我们让眉毛是普通的。我认为它是这样的：普通
然后我们设置嘴巴，
像我说过的一个微笑的嘴巴， okay? 这就是
我们的面部描述的默认值。
这就是我们的 MVC 中的模型。
现在这个模型中有趣的部分是
如何改变它? Okay, 如果它发生了改变, 我需要更新我的视图。
好的, 如果, 如果它从微笑变成了皱眉
我需要改变视图中的曲率。 所以我要
使用 didSet 的魔法就像我们之前做的那样
当模型发生改变的时候更新 UI。
因为这个值的类型是 FacialExpression,
如果这个变量中的任何属性发生了变化，
didSet 就会被调用, okay?
如果模型是一个类则不会调用 didSet。
所以庆幸它是个值类型。这部分将会被调用。
所以我们需要方法更新 UI。 我们可以在这里调用任何方法。
我喜欢把这个方法取名为 updateUI。
你可以取自己喜欢的名字。 这个方法应该是 private 的,
现在我们有了 updateUI 方法。
在它的内部我们需要更新 faceView。
好的, 如果我们想要更新我们的 faceview，我们需要
一个指向它的指针。 Okay, 我们该怎样创建一个视图的指针？
>> 单击并且拖动。
我们点击，然后拖动，对吧?
我们创建了一个 outlet。 动起手来吧.
打开 storyboard。我们已经得到了 face view。
控制器在这里。 我将要
把 faceView 拖动到这里然后创建一个
outlet。 取名为face view。它就是我的小人脸
okay。 我们在计算器项目中使用过它进行显示。 这既是我们的小人脸
我们点击这里的 okay 选项，然后我们得到了一个 outlet，
okay. 现在我们得到了一个指向人脸的指针.
接着我们会谈谈如何设置人脸的曲率以及
所有的这些逻辑，怎么样?
现在我们得到了这个指针以及 updateUI 方法。
我们可以自由讨论视图并且基于面部表情来配置视图。
所以我们该怎么做呢?
好吧，首先从眼睛开始吧。
如果面部描述中的眼睛是睁开的，
然后我们就需要向 faceView 发送一条消息告知它
眼睛睁开的选项是 ture。这很容易办到，
在眼睛的配置上模型和视图是相近的，
closed 选项的操作也很相近。 我们会把 faceview.eyesopen
设置为 false 但是 squinting 的情况该怎么办?
Okay, 实际上我们没有 faceView.squint 这样的属性, 好吧
我们办不到。 所以我只能写 eyes open 为 false.
如果你是 squinting（斜视）的表情, 眼睛闭上的状态更加贴近一些。
okay。 这是我们实现的最好方案，
这就是有时候控制器所发挥的作用。
这个视图可能并不能很好地展示视图，
它只能尽力做到最好。现在控制器是这样做的，我们可能会向 face view 中的某一位
发送一个请求，告诉它：嘿，伙计
我们想让视图能够展示 squinting
因为我们从模型中得到了一个 squinting 。某些视图可能就会照做，
好吧我们会采纳的，让我们看一下怎么做。
但是现在我们陷入了困境。
所以我们在处理 squinting 的时候只能让眼睛和 closed 中的情况一样。
那么其他两样东西会怎样呢? Okay，
我们有这些曲率需要处理，对吧?
我们想要写 faceView.mouthCurvature =
模型中关于嘴部曲率描述的值。
嘴巴的描述就像 grin 和 frown。
我们要做些什么?
我们该如何把它们转化成曲率?
现在我就来解决这个问题，
我想要创建一个轻量的私有的字典，
我会给它取名为 mouthCurvatures. Okay, 一对括号
并且我要让它等于一个字典。 记住，
我们可以使用一对方括号创建一个字典。
接下来我准备给这个字典设置一些键值来匹配
模型中的嘴巴曲率。
字典的值对应了视图中的嘴巴曲率。
好的， double 类型。举个例子，让我们增加一个新的成员
FacialExpression.Mouth.Frown。 Okay, 这是键值。
对应的值为 -1.0，这是该种状态的嘴巴的曲率。
看到了我所说的了吗?
我创建这个字典的目的是
映射模型与视图中的值。 那么 Grin（咧嘴）该是什么样?
顺便说一句， 当我咧嘴的时候, okay, 系统的类型推断已经推测出了字典的键是
一个 FacialExpression.Mouth 类型的。
因此我会这样做, 不需要每次都重复写前缀。
我可以只写 Grin。我们把 Grin 设定为 0.5。
所以它不是开怀大笑，只是微微一笑的程度。
开怀大笑的曲率是 1.0
一个 Smirk（傻笑）, 听起来有点像皱眉，
但是不是同一个表情。
我们把这种表情的值设为 -0.5
最后还有一个 Neutral（中立）的表情，把它的值 设为 0.0。Okay，
我把嘴巴的曲率装进了一个列表中。 现在，
完成了, 我可以把模型的 mouth 属性所提供的信息转换成
嘴巴视图的曲率。
Okay, 现在遇到了问题，你可以看到这里有一个报错。
所有人都能看到这里出问题了吧?
这是一个字典的查找。 字典的查找是什么?
它返回什么类型? 可选型。
耶， 这是个小麻烦。 它不是个可选型， okay?
所以我们该如何处理?
如果 Facial Expression 未来增加一些特性并且
这些新的表情不在这个字典里该怎么办?
我把它的默认值设为 0.0。 Okay?
记得在这里设置一个默认值
当你想要获取某个 double 类型的值，当它遇到nil时
你会得到一个默认的 double 值,
明白了吗? 这里加上 var。 Okay
我这里的处理很酷吧? 好的， 希望你在计算器项目中用到过它
这里和那个项目中的情况很像。
在字典中查找东西。 接下来
我要给眉毛的曲率做相同处理。 okay
eyeBrowTilt 等于 eyeBrowTilts（一个待生成的字典）
并且我要用一个 expression.eyebrows 作为索引。
然后当我们查找不到的时候
依旧设置为 0.0。
接下来我在这里定义一个私有变量，
取名为 eyeBrowTilts
用来处理 FacialExpression.Eyebrows。
这里需要填写的东西有 relaxed
我们要把 relaxed 解释成一个 CGFloat，值为 0.5，
这是一种放松的眉毛。注意
它不是 CGFloat，字面量是 0.5 okay 所以它是一个 double，
okay 现在眉毛的倾斜度是 double 类型了。
这里我们不想要一个 CGFloat 类型。
Okay .furrowed 是 -0.5 的倾斜度
.normal 我们设为 0。 Okay?
明白了吗? 所有人都明白了吗? 我们这里做了相同的查找。
我们把模型与视图进行了配对。
我们创建了一个为视图解释模型的控制器。 现在，
让我们继续并且运行程序，看看是什么样子。
Okay, 现在，这个表情看起来不太对。 因为，
如果你查看我们的模型就会发现，从模型中看眼睛应该睁开。
Okay, 这很棒。 眉毛是 normal。不。
屏幕上的眉毛不是 normal 的。没有有点皱。
并且嘴巴应该是 smile。 恩...， 不，这是一个 frown（愁眉苦脸） 的嘴型。
实际上，所有的这些面部表情不像是模型所表达的，
而是 storyboard 上的。
Okay，那么，为什么当我们初始化一个表情的时候
我们更新 UI 的逻辑没有实现呢？
这是因为当你通过构造器初始化一个值的时候
didSet 不会执行。 Okay?
当你稍后对它赋值的时候 didSet 才会执行。这是为什么 ？
因为你知道的在 Swift 中，当对象被初始化的时候，
在你对它做任何操作之前，
它必须被完全初始化。 所以理所当然的，当你想对 expression
做任何修改时，它必须被完全初始化。
Okay? 因此,这个对象已经初始化了, 但是
你的 updateUI 没有被调用，因为
expression 的初始化过程发生在
faceView controller 的初始化过程中。 现在， 如果我们稍后去设置 expression
updateUI 方法会被调用。 我们的 UI 会发生改变。所以，
我们该如何处理？ Okay。 有些事情无论如何我们都需要做
那就是
当我们的 faceView 的 outlet 被系统设置好的时候。
我们在它的 didSet 中更新我们的 UI。 Okay?
所以, 这里的 didSet 会在你的 MVC 创建不久之后
被 iOS 系统所调用, 它会关联这个 outlet。 Okay?
系统会钩住（hook up）这个 outlet，让它指向内存中的 faceView。
这样的话，只要这个过程发生，我们
就会持有我们的 faceView 了。现在我们可以更新 UI 了。 Okay，所以
当我们的模型发生变化以及我们的 faceView 第一次被系统钩住的时候，
我们都会更新 UI。 Okay。
我们经常把 didSet 与对象
写在同一行。
我们可以像上面这样写，这里我的代码保持这个写法
只是为了强调我们可以这么写
不过写在末尾是更常见的写法。
好的，现在运行一下，当 Swift（错说了）
iOS 系统基本启动并且钩住了 faceView 之后，
Boom~。 faceView 就更新到模型中描述的样子了， okay?
并且现在如果我们修改模型，让我们把
眉毛设置为 relaxed（放松），把嘴巴设置为 smirk（傻笑）。
让眼睛闭上。 Okay。 我们改变了模型中的
所有属性， 我们的视图会按照模型进行更新。
Okay, 就是这样 Okay? 都很棒吧?
所有人都理解我们对模型做了什么事情吧?
Okay。 让我们回到幻灯片。
让我们来讨论一下手势，并且我们将会回到项目中
并且向其中增加一些手势。
Okay。 所以，刚才我们看到了如何在视图中绘制。
我们画了嘴、眼睛和眉毛，所有的这一切。
我们知道如何做到这一点，
对吧? 我们在绘制的区域使用了
UIBezierpath，并不复杂。
那么手势呢? Okay? 这是用户在屏幕上的输入方式之一。
现在， 我们可以得到每一次单个手指触碰到屏幕时的
位置和运动轨迹，
这是可以实现。 Okay? 捕获手势有专门的 API，不过我们
几乎从来没有用过这些 API。 Okay? 我们为什么不用?
原因是用户认为当他们在屏幕上使用手势进行交互时
他们使用的手势是具体的，
比如滑动或者捏合。
这些是他们正在做的手势。
所以 iOS 系统中有一个抽象层
让你的应用可以把屏幕上的交互识别为对应的手势， okay?
所以你就可以得到这些手势并且
当它们产生的时候做相应的处理。 这些都是预定义的手势。
很棒的一点是，在每一个单独的应用中
滑动手势都是类似的。 Okay? 你知道的，就好比，
滑动的速度以及你需要滑动的距离，
在每一个应用中这些都是相同的，
这是因为每一个应用都用了相同的手势。 Okay,
如果你想要做自己的滑动手势，好吧，如你所知
多快速的动作算是滑动?
或者那是一个点击手势吗? 你必须去独自处理这些逻辑。
这将是一个痛苦的过程，并且
不同的程序间将会不一致。 Okay。所以
手势会被一个叫做 UIGestureRecognizer 的实例识别。
Okay，好名字。不过
UIGestureRecognizer 这个类本身是个抽象类。
你永远都不会实例化它。 取而代之的是一组
UIGestureRecognizer 的子类。
这些子类才是你需要根据具体的手势进行实例化的对象。
所以会有 pan gesture recognizer、
pinch gesture recognizer 以及 tap 和 swipe gesture
recognizer 等等。 Okay。现在当你想要使用一个识别器的时候，
它需要包含两部分, okay。
一个是在其上识别手势的 UIView。
把这个手势识别器加到视图上然后识别对应的手势。
所以这一步需要你
创建一个手势识别器然后
指定一个视图去使用它。 只有视图才能识别手势，
控制器不能识别手势。
Okay? 所以第一步就是创建你想要的手势识别器
按照你的想法配置它，并且
指派一些视图开始识别。 Okay?
然后第二步， 手势识别器识别了手势之后该做什么？
它需要一些处理。
这一步通过一个手势处理器（gesture handler）来完成。
现在你得到了手势识别器和手势处理器。
gesture handlers, okay? And the handler is called
as the recognizer goes through a basically a state machine
of recognizing this gesture. Okay, and
we'll talk about what that state machine looks like. But
it's called repeatedly,
the handler's gonna be called repeatedly, as the gesture
goes through the process of being recognized and
moving and all the things it does. Okay now usually
the first of these things the creating of a recognizer and
adding it to some
view is usually done by your controller. Okay.
It doesn't have to be done by your controller but
it's a good way for
its views. Okay the views are the minion of the controller
anyway. So, the controller wants to control its minions.
So, it might usually be the one that wants to
add the gesture recognizer to a view but
some views, the gesture recognition is so
fundamental to who they are that they add it themselves.
They add it themselves.
For example, ScrollView. Okay what would a ScrollView
be without a pan gesture. Just scrolling up and down it would
be useless it wouldn't even be a ScrollView anymore.
So ScrollView adds a pan gesture recognizer and
a pinch gesture recognizer to itself.
Probably in it's initializer. Okay but lot of the times your
controller that's adding the gesture,
again the controller can't do the recognition to gesture
only of you with the gesture recognizer can. But
the controller can add that gesture recognizer create and
add the gesture I can add it to one of its views in its
view. Okay, the second thing that handler that handles it.
Well that could be handled by the controller or
it might be handled by the view.
It could even be handled by someone else. Would never be
handled by your model because UI independent. But it could
be anyone in the controller view camps can handle it.
Generally, kind of, if the things that's the gesture is
doing is only modifying how the view displays itself,
like in our Faceview, it was just the scale of the view or
maybe somehow it was change in the color of the view.
Then the view is probably going to handle the gesture.
Okay, it's gonna both recognize it
with the recognizers and handle it. But if the gesture
is changing the model, then definitely the controller
would be the handler. Do you see why that is?
Because the view can't see the model, okay,
but the controller can. So the controller would set itself
as the recognizer of anything that's gonna affect the model.
We'll see that in the demo as well. Okay, so how do we
add a gesture to UIView? We've decided we want a view,
in this case lets say to recognize pan.
Okay a pan is putting your finger down on the screen and
moving it around without lifting it up.
And when you lift it up the pan is over. Kay,
that's what a pan is basically.
You're panning your finger around. On the screen.
All right? So if we wanted to do that. Well, one, so we have
to somewhere in our controller code add a pan gesture
recognizer to the view that we want the panning to happen in.
Okay? Well a great place to do that is in that didSet, okay?
Of the outlet. Cuz as soon as that view that
as soon as we get a pointer to it, let's immediately just add
we want to pan,
the gesture recognizer right there. Okay.
And we know that this didSet right here.
Okay we already saw this in the demo I just did. This
didSet, when you're doing it to an outlet. This gets called
only once. It gets called when iOS first hooks up that view.
Kay, perfect time to go add a gesture recognizer. Okay, so
we're gonna do that. First, we are going to create the pan
gesture recognizer. Okay, here is a concrete subclass of
UIGestureRecognizer called pan gesture recognizer.
It takes two arguments here. The first is who is going
to handle this gesture when I recognize it. Okay.
So this gesture pan gesture recognizer saying hey,
if I recognize a pan, who's gonna handle it for me?
And the answer is, self, so that's the controller. Okay.
Cuz there's an outlet in the controller so
the target itself means the controller is going to
handle this pan itself. Okay. The second argument here.
Is what method do you want me to invoke in self?
When this gets recognized, okay?
Now there's some kind of funky syntax here.
This has to be an Objective-C runtime compatible selector,
okay? That just means a selector, a method, okay,
the name of a method,
that is visible to the Objective-C runtime. Now, for
this to be visible to run to the Objective-C runtime,
this method must be in a class that inherits from NS object.
Remember I was talking about that NS object thing and
sometimes you're gonna need it, well,
here you would need it. Now you don't usually care about
that here, because this is almost always being handled by
either a UI view controller which definitely inherits from
NS objects or a UI view,
which definitely inherits from NS object, right? So
you usually don't care, okay? You're not usually going to be
trying to send this to some object that's a Swift object
that doesn't inherit from NS object. But this syntax here
means create an Objective-C compatible selector, okay?
Selector just means a kind of an identifier for a method.
And here is just the class, a dot, and then the name of
the method including the argument names. Don't forget
the argument names here. Now, this pan method that I'm gonna
show you on the next screen, it has one argument.
That argument is the pan gesture recognizer.
So just like when we have target action, and
we have a button that has the sender is sending itself.
Same thing here, when we have a pan gesture recognizer and
it starts to recognize, it sends this pan method
here to the view controller with itself as the argument.
Now you might say, why is this underbar right here?
Why don't I have the name of whatever this first keyword
is? And that's because I don't really care what that name is.
I just wanna make it clear,
I want the version of pan that has one argument. Now if I had
multiple, pan methods that had different first, names there,
then I would have to put the name in there. But I can put
underbar here because underbar in Swift means, I don't care,
whatever, okay? I don't really care what this is. It's
a substitute for I don't care. So I don't really care here.
So I just wanna introduce that you can do this underbar here.
But if I don't put this _:) here, then it's gonna try and
call a pan method that has no arguments.
So be careful, if you want the one that has the gesture
recognizer as an argument, you gotta put that in there, okay?
So that's specifying the selector. And then I just turn
on this recognizer by taking the view, this is the UIView,
this pannableView, okay? And adding this thing I created as
a gesture recognizer, okay? As soon as I add that,
this view is gonna start recognizing pan gestures,
okay? And when it does, it's gonna send this method to
self which is the controller, got it? Okay, makes sense,
that's what we're doing there? All right, so now,
let's talk about how we implement this handler?
This method right here, this pan thing, okay?
What does that look like to implement? To,
to understand how we're gonna implement such a method, we
needed to understand a little bit more about the concrete
subclasses of UI gesture recognizer. So
let's look at pan, okay? So pan, UIPanGestureRecognizer,
it has a few methods on it that are specific to panning,
okay? For example, it has translationInView.
It takes a UIView and tells you how far the pan has moved
in that view's coordinate system, okay?
Which is exactly what you want for a pan cuz you wanna know
where you are, so calls wanted to know how far you moved?
It even has velocity in view, we'll tell you how fast
the pan is happening, okay? If you're ripping it around
versus going really really really really slow.
Like if you had a drawing app, when you're going really slow,
you might be drawing really carefully.
And if you're zipping it around,
now you're making big arcs or something, who knows? And
it even has set translation, which is setting this.
Why would you ever want to set this?
Well, if you don't set this, okay? Then this translationVew
is going to be the cumulative translationInView,
okay? It's how far the pan has moved since it started,
the cumulative thing. If you what you want instead is, how
much it's changed since last time you told me about it,
okay? You can constantly reset this to zero.
If you constantly reset this translation to zero,
then the next time you get it,
it's gonna be the translation incremental, okay? Tiny bit,
little tiny bit it moves since the last time, okay?
So you'll see in the demo that we we will reset this to zero
every time, cuz we just want the incremental panning, okay?
All right, so the abstract superclass of UI pan gesture
also provides a very important var, which is the state.
Okay, I told you that these gesture recognizers go through
a state machine, okay? And this is how you can find out
in your handler what state the gesture is in.
So they all start around in this state possible, okay?
UIGestureRecognizerState.Poss- ible. Then for
a discrete gesture, like a swipe, once the swipe happens,
it immediately goes to the state recognized, okay?
It recognized the swipe. So
your handler gets called, the state will be recognized. For
a continuous gesture like a pan or a pinch, okay? It goes
to the state Began as soon as the pan gets held down, and
as soon as the pan starts moving it keeps going to
the state Changed. Change, change, change, change,
change, the handler keeps getting called over and
over and over and over and over with Changed, okay?
And every time this translation is changing, okay?
And then, when the finger goes up, then it goes to Ended.
Make sense? Now there's couple other states here, Failed and
Cancelled. Like if you're doing the middle of a pan and
a phone call comes in, okay?
Then you're gesture is gonna get cancelled,
okay? So you might or might not have to deal with that.
If you're dealing with your pan incrementally,
then who cares if it gets interrupted?
You were moving the thing incrementally.
If you are dealing with your pan with some big
thing at the end, when the pan ends, then you better do in
here what you were gonna do when it ended, okay?
But a lot of times you don't care cuz you're doing all
the work in Changed so Cancelled and Failed is
just like Ended but you don't notice the finger going up.
Well, no big deal. Okay, so now that I have all this
information about a pan gesture,
how do I make a handler that handles a pan gesture, okay?
This is what the code would look like. This code is gonna
be in my controller because I said the controller is gonna
handle the pan. And first I'm gonna look at the state, okay?
Of the, okay, yeah, I'm sorry, here's that pan_:),
you see, this pan takes an argument,
okay? Instead of underbar there I could have put gesture
because that's what I called it here, gesture, but
I don't care. But, this one take an argument,
you could have pan with no arguments here and
nothing there and this would not pass the pan gesture along
as an argument. But, here I need the pan gesture,
cuz I need to know how far the pan is gone, okay? So, next
I'm gonna switch on the state that the pan gesture is in and
if it's Changed Or Ended, then I am going to update something
in my controller, okay? Otherwise,
I'm gonna ignore it, okay? If it's Cancelled or Failed or
if it Began, I don't care. I'm only interested when it moves,
okay? So that's why I'm only looking at this.
Now, I wanna show you this kinda cool thing in Switch.
Hopefully you got this in your homework? But there's this
thing, fallthrough. Remember that Swift cases
don't fall through to the next case like they do in C, okay?
But you can force them to fall through with fallthrough.
Now, I probably wouldn't write code like this,
I would just say case.Changed, .Ended, okay?
That's a easier way to do this, but
I just wanted to show you fallthrough, okay? All right,
so here inside, when things have Changed or Ended,
I'm gonna get the translation in the pannableView. Okay,
remember this to that outlet? I'm gonna get that translation
from the gesture. And then I'm gonna go and
update something that depends on where the pan is.
I've got, I know where the pan, how far it has moved. So
I'm just gonna update what, something that needs that.
And then I'm gonna set the translation back to 0.
Okay, this also could be CGPoint.Zero if you want. But
see, I'm gonna set it back to 0 so
that the next time I get called to my handler,
next time it comes back around, this translation will
be the incremental translation from the last time it sent it
to me. Everybody get that? Please? Okay? All right.
So that's it. That's what the handler looks like.
Pretty straight forward. Okay. We'll see this in the demo,
it's not too bad, okay? Let's briefly talk about some of
the other concrete gestures besides pan,
there's pinches. Pinches is two fingers down,
pinching in and out like this, okay? And here what
you're getting instead of the translation, it is the scale.
So if I start my fingers here and I bring them out twice as
wide that will be a scale of two. If I start him here and
move him in half way, that's a scale 0.5.
Okay, so I'm scaling whatever on my screen and again I can
get velocity, how fast I'm pinching. Rotation is two
fingers turning them, okay. Like you're turning a knob and
it will tell you how many radians you've turned, okay.
And again velocity, how fast you're turning. Swipe gesture,
okay. The swipe gesture you usually have to configure
before you use it. You have to say, do you want a left
going swipe, or right going swipe or up or down. Okay, and
also two fingers swipe, or one finger or three fingers okay.
You have to configure that then you add the gesture
recognizer and it will only recognize it if all those
things are true. Two finger swipe up has all the,
it has to be a two finger swipe up.
Otherwise it doesn't recognize it, okay. So
that's swipe. Tap, which seems like it would be discreet,
is not quite a discreet gesture, but
you also configure it with how many taps. You know,
is it a single tap, or a double tap? And two fingers,
or one? Okay, you configure that, add it, and here, you're
gonna look for .ended to find out when the tap has happened,
okay. That's because a tap actually has intermediate
things going on like a double tap has a, the first tap. And
then the second tap. And it might go through a state
change that will call your handler, but
it's not done yet. Okay and you can't look at recognized,
at recognized with tap because it's not a discreet gesture.
Because it goes through those intermediate phases.
So you really look for .ended for tap, okay.
All right, so let's do a demo. Let's see all this in action
with our facet and what we're gonna do. First, I'm gonna add
a pinch gesture that makes our face get bigger and
smaller. Okay, we're just gonna pinch in and out and
adjust our scale. And then I'm gonna add a pan gesture.
Actually I'll probably do a swipe.
Let's do a swipe gesture, that modifies our model, okay.
We're gonna use it to make our model happier or sadder.
If I make it happier or sadder, then we'll adjust our
face view, okay. Let's do that. Back to our facet here.
All right, so how are we gonna do this?
First thing we need to do is add a gesture recognizer,
okay. And again I said inside faceView didset is a good
place to do that. So now I'm gonna expand this back out.
Because I'm gonna add more code than just that one,
thing here, okay. And I'm still gonna update you,
UI here, but I'm also going to add a gesture recognizer.
I know that this didSet is only gonna be called once
when my outlet is first hooked up to my UI, so that's perfect
cuz I only wanna add the gesture recognizer once. And
I know that the faceView is the guy who has to recognize
the gesture. Only views can recognize gestures. So
I'm going to add a gesture recognizer.
Okay and you can see that when you add a gesture
recognizer to a UI view it takes
a gesture recognizer an argument. So I'm gonna create
one here, a UI pinch gesture recognizer, okay. And
that recognizer takes that target and action as they are,
as the two arguments, right? So the target here,
in this case, since that pinch is only changing the scale
of the view, it's not changing my model,
I'm gonna let the face view handle this thing itself. Now,
for the FaceView to handle it, it's going to have to make
some sort of gesture handler available to my controller.
So it's gonna have the public method right,
that handles a pinch.
So we're gonna have to add that to FaceView which will do
next. And the action here is gonna be a selector,
it's gonna be a FaceView selector. FaceView selector.
And I'm gonna call it changeScale, okay.
And I am definitely going to need the argument there.
So I'm gonna do that, as well, okay.
Maybe this is a little easier to see if I do this.
Like that. Okay. So it gives me an error here because
of course this method doesn't exist. So it's nice that it
actually checks to make sure that this exist, okay.
So let's go ahead and add this method right here, okay. This
is the method that's going to handle when a pinch happens,
okay. We're gonna put that in our FaceView, so
I'm gonna go over here to FaceView.
Put it up here towards the top since it's gonna be public,
okay. It has to be public, because the controller
wants the gesture handler to call it. So changeScale. It's
going to have a recognizer as its argument, okay?
That UIPinchGestureRecognizer. Okay,
so it's nice that when we're asked to handle the gesture,
the recognizer is passed along to us.
And, this is really easy to implement,
I'm just gonna switch on the recognizer state. And
if the state is changed or
ended, and yes you can do it that way in switches, in Swift
you can have multiple things there. If it's changed or
ended then I'm just gonna set my scale to be multiplied
by the recognizer scale. Okay cuz here's my scale up here.
And so if this pinch goes 2.0 twice as wide,
then I want my scale to be twice of what it was. And
if it goes down to 0.5, I want my scale
to be 0.5 of what it was. Okay, but this is gonna
be repeatedly called as that thing is moving in and out, so
I need to make sure here that I reset the recognizer scale
to 1.0 all the time. So that, as it moves out,
it's going to be give me the incremental scale in and out.
Because I'm actually applying the scale change every single
time it moves, every .Changed here I'm applying the scale,
okay. Now of course we need to have the default,
state which is cancel, it covers cancelled and began and
all those things.
And it those case statuses I'm just gonna do nothing because
I'm actually tracking the scale and implementing it
as it goes along, so I don't even care when it ends, okay.
I mean, it's nice when the fingers go up to do that one
last adjustment of the scale but it's not crucial. Okay,
and if we were cancelled, we wouldn't get that opportunity
anyway. Okay, everyone understand that?
This is a public method, yeah. >> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Well, yeah, see I'm, this
is why I ask three or four times, everybody getting this.
And everyone was kind of like yeah, I think so.
Okay. The reason for this is, if I don't do this, okay,
then as I pinch, I'm gonna get the cumulative scale, okay. So
let's say I start here, okay. And I start moving it out,
moving it out. And it's getting called changed,
change, change, change, okay. First time it's 1.1, 1.2, 1.3,
1.4, 1.5, 1.6, 2.0, okay.
So it's getting called seven times with all those numbers.
Imagine if I took my scale and multiplied it times by 1.0.
And then I multiplied it times 1.2, 1.3, 1.4.
Now the scale's getting gigantic. Okay,
that's not what I want. What I want is the incremental scale.
So if I keep resetting it to 1, then when it gets a little
bigger, I'm gonna get 1.01 again, okay? Reset to 1,
1.01 again, you see? Exactly, I'm not by the scale. Now,
the alternative is, I could just have the pinch do nothing
until you let go and then I could set the scale, okay?
But, since I'm doing it incrementally,
I have to keep resetting it to 1, okay? Good question. All
right, so now if we go back to our FaceViewController,
you'll see that we don't have an error here anymore on this
line because we've actually defined this handler, okay? So
now when we run, and we pinch. We're gonna update the scale,
hopefully, of our face.
So here's our face. He doesn't look very happy, but
I'm going to make him smaller, so we won't notice, okay? Now,
you might ask, how am I gonna pinch with my mouse, okay?
I've got my mouse here, I can't, just a little,
how am I gonna do it? And the answer is, Option, okay?
If you're running the simulator and
you hold down Option, look. Two fingers come up there,
okay? Now you can mouse down and drag and it's like you're
pinching. You see, pinching in pinching out,
okay? Got it, so you can see these gesture hands
are super easy to implement, okay? We probably had four
lines of code there, of actual lines of code. All right,
now, let's do another gesture recognizer, okay? Let's have
this one modify our model. So what I'm gonna do here is,
I'm gonna make it so that when I swipe down, he gets sadder.
And when I swipe up,
he gets happier in a model sense, okay? Okay,
I'm gonna make the model happier.
I'm not gonna move my mouth curvature. I'm gonna change
the model. Now of course, every time I change the model,
that's going to change my mouth curvature. So
it's gonna work. But we're gonna change the model.
So to do that, I'm gonna do a swipe gesture.
Now, a swipe gesture we have to configure.
So I'm to create a local variable to hold it, okay?
I am gonna call this local variable,
my happierSwipeGestureRecognizer,
and so I say UISwipeGestureRecognizer.
SwipeGestureRecognizer and same arguments though,
Oops,
target and action, okay? So the target here, okay,
is not going to be the faceView because it modifies
the model, it's gonna be self. Okay,
controller has to be the one handling this one, okay?
And the action, which is the selector, is going to be
a FaceViewController selector, not a FaceView one.
And we'll call this thing we'll do,
we'll make this be the happier one, so this is swipe up, so
we'll call this increaseHappiness, okay?
And I don't need the swipe gesture
because it's either gonna be recognized or not. So
I'm not gonna have any arguments
to that increaseHappiness method, okay?
Okay, I'll do the same thing here so
you can see this a little better, okay? So this is not,
this guy right here is not going to have any arguments.
So that's gonna be a func, okay? increaseHappiness,
no arguments. And when the increaseHappiness happens,
what are we gonna do to our model, okay? Well,
we're just gonna say that our facial expression's mouth
equals the expression's mouth.happierMouth.
Okay, so if you look at our facial expression over here,
okay, mouth okay?
This enum has two methods, sadderMouth and happierMouth,
which will take the current mouth and make it sadder or
happier and return a new mouth, okay? So
it's just gonna go more happy or less happy along here.
Okay, so we got that. Now so that's gonna be fine.
This swipe gesture though, we have to add it to our view.
We have to do addGestureRecognizer.
We haven't done that. And we also have to configure it.
So let's configure it. This is happier. So
I'm gonna have the hype, the SwipeGestureRecognizerDirect-
ion. Okay, which is the direction of the swipe,
= .Up. Okay, so you're swiping up, that's for
happier, and now we, and
it will have it be a single finger swipe, not two. And so
now I can just say faceView.addGestureRecognizer-
(happierSwipeGestureRecogniz- er), okay?
Make sense there? All right, let's go try this.
Now notice every time we change the expression here,
it's gonna automatically update our UI because of this
didSet. You see that? We changed this expression, boom,
updateUI. So, let's try it. All right, so,
hopefully this is still working.
Pinching, yes, still working. Now I'm gonna swipe up and
sure enough, he's getting happier and happier. Okay, but
we better do swipe down also, okay?
We don't have all only swipe up, let's get swipe down in
there. In fact, I'm gonna do that by copying and
pasting because it's almost the same as this.
I'm just gonna replace this happier here with sadder.
And instead of it being an up swipe, it's gonna be a down
swipe. And instead of increasing the happiness,
it's going to decrease the happiness.
So I need a new method here called decreaseHappiness.
And this one's going to get the sadderMouth, okay?
Everyone understand, it's real important to understand here
that we have recognizers that as they're being handled,
they're being handled by the controller.
And the controller's modifying the model. And since, and
every time the model gets modified, it calls updateUI.
updateUI is the thing that's going to update, in this case,
the mouth curvature. Everybody understand that flow? Okay, so
let's make sure that swipe down is working. All right,
so swipe down, sad. Swipe up, happy, okay? Sad,
happy, got it? All right, let's do one more gesture.
This one, when you tap, he's gonna open and close his eyes.
Every tap will toggle the opening and closing the eyes.
Now I'm gonna do this one a little bit different, because
we added all these gesture recognizers in code here.
You see how this adding GestureRecognizer in code?
You can actually add these things in your storyboard,
okay? So let's go over to our storyboard, right here,
okay? Let's get our controller onscreen at the same time,
Automatic. So here's our controller over here.
Here's our faceView over here. If I wanna add a gesture to my
faceView right here from my storyboard, I go over here to
the bottom, same place I get buttons and things like that.
If you scroll way down, you'll see there are gesture
recognizers here, you see? Rotation, pinch, swipe, pan.
Here's tap. I'm gonna take tap out and drag it onto the view
I want to recognize the tap, which is my faceView. And
when you do that, it actually appears along the top here.
See that Tap Gesture Recognizer right there? And
you can even inspect it. You could set how many taps,
how many touches, okay, how many fingers. Okay,
you can also Ctrl+drag from it over here, let's do it down
a little lower, here. Okay, you can Ctrl+drag and
create the gesture recognizer action, okay, right here.
So I'm gonna call this toggleEyes,
okay? And the argument,
I'm gonna make it to a tap gesture instead of any object.
We all know to get rid of the any object in these little,
dialogues. Okay, so here's my tap gesture right here.
Let's go ahead and go back to full screen,
okay? So, here's my tap gesture for toggleEyes. So,
in here I need to toggle my eye, so I'm just going to say,
if the recognizer's state is ended. Okay? So the tap ended,
so I'm gonna take action here and do the toggle.
Then, depending on what the expression's current eyes are,
if it, they're open, then I'm gonna be the,
make the expression's eyes be closed. And
if it's, if the eyes are closed, then I'm gonna make
the expression's eyes open. And if the express,
if the expression is squinting then I'm going to do nothing
cuz I don't know how to handle squinting. Okay make
sense? Sorry notice I used recognizer.state here.
By default when you Ctrl+drag it calls a thing sender.
I really like to call this recognizer. So
that you remember that it's a recognizer that we're dealing
with here, okay, gesture recognizer. Okay so
let's try that. All right,
your face. We can make him happier and we can open and
close his eyes. Okay? Maybe later in the quarter,
we'll talk about animation,
we'll talk about animating the eye it will turn so he blinks.
Okay? And I'm gonna post code after lecture because
the time here I wanna make sure we get to the next thing.
Where I'm gonna show how to do rotation to move those
eyebrows. Okay?
So, rotate the eyebrows down or rotate them up. Okay?
I'll show you how to do a rotation disk, so
that'll be in the code that I post. Okay,
any questions about gestures? Pretty straightforward, okay?
All right, let's get back to our
slides. >> Is
that odd gesture recognizer code automatically
added to the UIView? >> Okay so
the question was is that eye gesture recognize your code
that I put in there do the tap.
Is it already automatically added to the UIView?
And the answer, you mean the add gesture recognizer?
Cog it made? >> Yeah.
>> Yeah, that, basically,
when you can control,
when I dragged the tap gesture onto the face view,
the add gesture recognizer was gonna happen. Make sense?
that made it so
Good question, though. Okay, so, back to the slides here.
Now we're gonna start talking about MVCs working together.
Okay? This is a slide from when I was talking about MVCs
and we talked about we wanted to build big apps, and
we're gonna do that with multiple MVCs.
So, we're gonna start talking about how we actually do that.
All right? The way we combine MVCs as
I talked about before is that we're gonna have an MVC, okay?
Whose view is made up of other MVCs. Okay?
Now iOS provides for us some MVCs that are like this.
Okay, MVCs whose view is other MVCs. Now, it is possible for
you to create your own MVCs that have other MVCs as view,
but it is really beyond the scope of this class.
Okay? So in this class we are only gonna use the ones that
are provided by iOS. These MVCs that use other MVCs as
their view. Now specifically, we are gonna talk about
TabBarController. Everyone know what that is all right?
You've seen that in an iOS
AVS the little tabs on the bottom and each time you click
on a different tab, what appears on top?
A different MVC, okay. Also SplitViewController mostly you
see this on an iPad you can all see on an iPhone 6 plus.
This is where you're splitting your screen into two halves.
Okay, not really halves.
Two parts, one side's usually smaller that the other, okay?
So, each side a different MVC. So, you see how
we combine two MVCs right there. And then, of course,
UINavigationController, the number one combiner of MVCs.
Okay, this is something where you have
an MVC, it's got a button in it, you click it, and a new
MVC appears, where there's a back button at the top,
and you've click it to go back to the one you were on. Okay?
See navigation controllers in almost every iOS app that's
ever been designed ever except for
maybe games that are all one MVC.
You're gonna see navigation controllers. Okay so
let's talk a little bit about how all these things work.
So let's talk about the TabBarControllers and
the simplest of them all, right?
You've seen this right it's got the tabs along
the bottom here. I've got this one the dashboard this is
the health app I think. Got the dashboard selection here,
and this entire space is being owned and managed
by a Dashboard MVC. Not the TabBarController MVC, but
the dash part MVC. And in fact this dashboard is controlling
not only the contents of here. But it tells you,
our TabBarcontroller what icon to put here and
what word to put here. Okay? These tabs over here, these
other tabs are, their contents are controlled by other MVCs.
Okay? So, this var, tab bar item that you see right there.
It's kind of a little bag of goodies that each MVC,
remember an MVC is controlled by its controller.
So this is a method in UIViewController.
And it has things in there like the icon and the text for
the tab, okay? In TabBarItem. So you can take a look at
the TabBarItem and you'll immediately see. What's going
on there. All right. So, let's click on a different one,
like Health Data, and we get a completely different MVC here.
This is the Health Data MVC.
Completely unrelated to this one. Okay?
Utterly and completely unrelated to this one.
Okay? Here, one thing to notice about this is,
if there are more than five tabs down here.
This actually still works. It'll automatically replace
the 5th one with a tab here that says More.
And when you click on More it'll have a UITabBar
controlled UI in here that has all the other tabs in here.
And you can pick them. Or you can actually choose to put
them down here, okay, which four you want down here. Okay,
and that happens automatically for you.
You don't have to do anything to make that work.
I don't really recommend UIs that have more than five tabs
down here. It's a little bit of a pain for people to have
to have that more thing, but it's not out of the question.
Obviously the functionality's in there.
If you can do it without it, that'd be nice. Okay here's
a couple more tabs here is the source's one another MVC
another so these are four completely separate MVCs.
They have nothing to do with each other okay.
The only thing that might link them maybe they share a model.
That's possible okay but maybe even not.
Okay so a tab bar is what's you gonna use when you
have MVCs they're completely unrelated. Okay? All right.
What about SplitViewController?
So, SplitViewController puts two MVCs side by side. So,
let's imagine your calculator was a graphing calculator.
Okay, instead of just a calculator,
it could graph, what's going on over here.
Then on the left here, you'd have your calculator, and
on the right, you'd have a totally different MVC.
Which is a graph view calculator,
calculator graph view, or something like that. Okay,
we call this one on the left the Master View Controller and
we call the one on the right the Detail View Controller.
Okay, when you take your iPad here and
you rotate it, you still get both. Its just that
the detail will usually take over the whole screen. And
you can slide from the right, you kind of swipe in from, or
sorry from the left. And you'll see that the master
slides in on top of the detail. Okay. So
that's what view, how it, how it arrange.
NavigationController, so NavigationController it's like
a stack of cards. Okay? Where each card is a different MVC.
So here I have an all settings MVC,
okay, inside of a navigation controller Now,
this navigation controller is responsible for
drawing this title bar at the top, okay?
This whole area in the top where it says Settings. But
it's not responsible for the actual contents
of what's in there. That word Settings is determined,
just like in tab bar situation, with by this MVC,
okay? This MVC down here has a, property on it. It's view,
it's view controller called Navigation Item. And
navigation item has properties in it like the title, the,
any buttons that go here, maybe a back button title,
those kind of things.
All would be in this navigation item of this all
Settings MVC, not of the navigation controller,
right? So, here if I touched on General and
I wanted the general settings, then of course, the general
settings would slide in, okay? And replace the whole contents
here with a general settings MVP, yet another new MVC. And
notice the back button by default will be set to have
the name of the previous MVC. That other MVC is still in
the navigation controller, it's just underneath, okay?
So this is stack of cards, I just put another MVC on top,
so the other one's still there, okay? And
you can also put toolbar items at the bottom here, okay?
That's also controlled by whatever MVC is showing.
So this tool by are, barItems is a property on
UIViewController, it's an array of UI toolbarItem, and
it'll let you put toolbarItems down here, okay? Little,
small buttons, okay? So again, if I click, let's say sorry.
Yeah, the back button got the title there, but you can also
set the title to something different if you want,
okay? So let's say I clicked on Accessibility right here,
I get another new MVC. Now I have three MVCs on my stack,
okay? Let's go ahead and click on another one here,
a larger text right there. Now I got another one, so
now I have four MVCs on my stack, okay? Now,
I'm going to go and click on Accessibility,
up in the top there, the back button. Now what happens? Now,
this MVC gets thrown away, in the trash, out of the heap,
gone forever, okay? Now there's only three MVCs left,
okay? The other one's completely gone.
It's important to understand on a MVC,
when you go back, the one that got thrown off literally gets
thrown away, okay? And so, if we go back again, now that one
got thrown away. Now there's only two MVCs in the world,
okay, on top of each other. And of course if we go back to
the beginning, now we get back to here, this MVC we'll call
the root view controller of the navigation controller.
It's just one that's at the bottom of the deck. Okay,
it's always in there. Okay, so lets talk about how that
navigation controller works from our MVC standpoint, okay?
Let's say I have an MVC here. And I just have too much
functionality. I just can't fit all the functionality in
my view, I need to put this somewhere else.
So I create another MVC, okay? Cuz somebody has to control
this extra functionality. So there's another controller,
okay? A whole other MVC here, okay? And I want these two,
they're related, okay? So somehow in this view, I,
I get to this UI because this UI kinda all goes together in
some way. It's not related in some mechanism, maybe it's
master detail kind of effect or something like that.
So how am I gonna make this work, okay? So
I'm using UINavigationController. And
here's a UINavigationController.
It's view, looks like this, okay? It's blank, okay?
It's got room up here though for a title,
back button, maybe some other buttons over here. But
it never lives like this because there is an outlet
called rootViewController, okay? Which is hooked up to
some MVC. And when it's hooked up, the contents of the view
of the navigation controller are the contents of this MVCs
view. Right, make sense, kinda obvious? Now
there's probably some button in here that if I touch it,
means I wanna show this UI over here, I want this MVC. So
if I touch it, what the navigation controller does,
it moves over here, shows this view.
This one's still around, okay? It's just not showing but
it's still in the UINavigationController stack,
okay? It shows this guy right here.
Notice we get this automatic back button right there.
If we press that back button, okay? Then it's going to
go back here, and look what happened to this MVC.
Gone, okay, completely got eliminated. If I press this
button again to go back, it would create a new one,
okay? A brand new instance of this MVC, okay? [INAUDIBLE] So
that's how the Navigation Controller is working from
an MVC standpoint. All right, [COUGH] now in these MVCs,
how do I get at the other MVCs that are, I'm sharing
the navigation controller or the split view controller or
the tab bar controller, how do I get to them,
send them messages, talk to them in some way?
And the answer is through this very important var in UI
viewController, okay? Sorry, in UI tab bar controller,
UI split view controller, and UI navigation controller,
they all have this var.
And it's an array of view controllers,
it's all the view controllers in this thing. All
the tabs in the tab bar, both this master and the detail and
the split view, all the things on the navigation stack. And
navigation controller. It can be an optional,
like the tab bar case, it can be an optional.
I don't think it's an optional for the other two.
You're have to look at documentation there for
that. But in a tab bar this is just the array.
I believe it's from left to right, okay?
So it's all the MVCs from the left tab to the right, and if
you have more then it spills into the order in the more
tab. For split view, [0] in this array is the master and
[1] is the detail. And for navigation controller,
[0] is the bottom card and 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7 is going up the stack, okay? So the last one that's
visible would be the last one in this array, okay? Got it?
Notice this is set table, it's get and set but we usually
don't set our viewControllers this way, okay?
Like split view, we usually wire it up in our storyboard.
In navigation controller we're usually navigating to those
other MVCs and tab bar we also set up in our storyboard,
okay? So, it is set table but usually we're getting them.
But, so that's great but if I'm inside
a splitViewController, how do I get the splitViewController
I'm in so that I can access this property? And
the answer is UIViewController has these three very important
properties, tabBarController, splitViewController and
navigationController, they're all optionals. They will tell
you the splitViewController you are in, if you're in one.
If you're not, it'll be nil, okay? It will also tell
you this one, what navigation controller you're in if you're
in one? And you could be in both a splitViewController and
a navigationController. Imagine a splitVieController
where the master is actually the navigationController
that you can navigate through, okay? So you can have
a navigationController inside a splitVewController and
any MVC that's in that navigationController,
this would be nil, non nil and this would also be non nill,
okay? Cuz it would be in, in both of those things. And
once you get the splitViewController or
navigationController in, you can
find the other MVCs using this thing up here.
So for example, if I have an MVC and it's the master in
a splitViewController, and I want to get the detail. I can
just say, splitViewController? Because it might be nil and
this a chaining. Remember, everyone hopefully remembers
chaining? I'm gonna get the view controllers, sub one.
Remember, number one is the detail. And that's gonna give
me the detail of the splitViewController I'm in,
if I'm in one, otherwise it'd be nil, this would be nil.
So this actually says detailVC: UIViewController,
but this would be detailVC: UIViewController? Okay?
This would be optional. That's a bug in the slides there.
Okay, so, how do we wire up these MVCs, how do we get this
all set up? Let's take a look at Split View and briefly,
Navigation Controller. And then on, in our next
lecture we'll talk about how we transition between these
various MVCs. Okay. especially in Navigation Controller,
how do we put things, more things on the stack? How do we
make it go to the next, thing? So, for split view controller,
you basically drag a split view controller out of your
little utilities, object palette in interface mode.
Just drag it out. Now, when you drag out a split view
controller, you're gonna get a whole bunch of other MVCs.
It tries to help you out by giving you Navigation
controllers with table views in it,
all that stuff, just delete all that stuff, okay?
You just want the split view controller. You, it's being
a little too helpful for the, you most of the time there,
kkay? So you're gonna drag that out, and then you're just
gonna Ctrl + drag from the split control, view controller
to the master, and the detail, okay? Looks like this.
Here's my split view control and
I dragged it out of the utilities pane.
I'm just Ctrl + dragging to my calculator, for example,
to be my master. When I do, this popover will appear and
the only two things that make sense to pick are master and
detail. Okay, these are the only two choices that make any
sense. Those don't make sense here.
So let's pick the master. It's gonna create a connection,
the master connection. Ctrl+drag down here. I'm gonna
pick Detail. It's gonna make a connection down there. Voila,
I've wired up my split view controller, okay?
All right, but split view can only do what it does on iPad,
right? There's really, on most iPhones, everything except for
the iPhone 6 Plus,
there's really not enough room to have a split view. So
we want to simultaneously put the MVCs that are our master
in details with split view into Navigation Controllers.
And then iOS is smart enough, if it's on iPhone only, okay,
iPhone 6 or iPhone 5 or something like that, it knows
not to use the split view controller, it will only use
the Navigation Controllers. Okay, so let' take a look and
see what that looks like. So,
here I've got that thing I just showed you, right?
The calculator, the graph,
here's the split view controller.
I'm just gonna take this guy and
put it inside a Navigation Controller. And
the way we do that, easiest way is to select it and
then say embed in Navigation Controller. Same way we did
embed in stack view, but here since we're choosing
a whole controller, we can't embed it in a stack view.
So we're gonna say embed in Navigation Controller. And
it's gonna embed this thing into a Navigation Controller,
which is gonna look like this. So split the controller,
this is still the master. Now this Navigation Controller,
this MVC, is the master and its root view controller
is the calculator. Okay, and the cool thing about this,
like I say, if you run this in an iPhone it'll ignore this
and just have your calculator in a Navigation Controller and
when you try to show a graph it'll put this as a stack,
a card stack, on this Navigation Controller.
Isn't that cool? Okay, so that way it'll work on both
platforms. Exactly the same storyboard.
All right, okay, yes, I'm just noticing, I'm mentioning here,
you can put this one inside a Navigation Controller too.
You don't really need to,
okay? Only the thing that is the root view controller
really needs to be inside of it, but
if you put it then you'll get a nice title on the top.
You see you've got a title there,
a calculator, you'll get that nice title here, even in
the split view case. The only thing to watch out for
is this detail will now be a Navigation Controller,
not a calculator graph controller.
You always have to be careful of that case. All right, so
that's it for today.
On Wednesday, we'll talk about what are called segues.
That's how we transfer from one MVC to another,
either in the split view or the Navigation Controller
case. We'll do a demo which is going to extend face it, okay,
it's going to call, be called emotions as you can imagine,
we're gonna show some emotions on our faces. Then I'm going
to start talking about the view controller lifecycle,
that's part of the two methods that I always delete
when I start a new thing.
We'll learn what those are, so you don't have to delete them.
Friday, really good optional section, which is source code
management. Remember I've been not clicking that button.
Now you'll know what that is.
And you can click that button from now on, if you want,
after Friday. And then next week,
we'll talk about protocols, delegations, scroll view,
all kinds of wonderful stuff. Okay, that's it. I'll be here
if you have any questions. >> For
more, please visit us at stanford.edu.